OK, so let's talk about the three types of
float in this video.
Now, three types of float, then.
There is something called the Total Float,
the Free Float, and the Project Float.
So we already talked about the Total Float
before, right?
Now with discussion
in the Forward Pass and
Backward Pass, we
talked about the total float.
So anyway, let's do a quick review here
what Total Float is.
Now the official definition of Total Float
is basically the time and activity can be
delayed, without delaying the end date of
the project.
How long can an
activity be delayed without
delaying the actual
end date of the project?
So if I go to the next slide, so this is
the network diagram that we just looked at
and this one is the zero method, always
easier to understand with the zero method.
So the total float then is the total float
that we calculated for each activity.
B has a total flow of three.
C has a total flow of three.
B can be delayed back to three days.
No impact on the schedule.
No impact on the end date.
If G gets delayed by one day, no impact on
the end date, no impact on the schedule.
So if I go back, so the total float then
is how long an activity can be delayed
without delaying the schedule, without
delaying the end date of the project.
I remember a lot of times they'll ask you
what is a total float of a path,
of an entire path.
And so if they ask you what is a total
float of, say, A, B, C, I, the total float
of A, B, C, I, in this case, would be
three.
You never, never add float values
together.
They are not cumulative.
It's always wherever is the highest float.
So A, B, C, I, the float will be three,
because that is the highest float.
I mean, B and C have the
same float, so by default,
three will be the
total float for that path.
If the floats are different, then it's
wherever is the highest one.
So, A, B, F, I, for example, right, path
A, B, FI, total float will still be three.
F has a float of one, B has a float of
three, total float will not be four,
total float will be three, wherever is the
highest float.
Remember, never, never add float values
together.
Okay, so if we go back
to the previous slide
again, let's talk about
this term here, free float.
Now, free float is the time
and activity can be delayed
without delaying the early
start of the successor activity.
How long can an
activity be delayed without
delaying the early
start of the next activity?
right the successor activity all right so
let's look at this on the network diagram
if we look at b b has a total flow of
three right we establish that it has a
total floor of three however b finishes on
day six c will start on day six so how
long can b be delayed without
delaying the early start of
c the answer is zero so b
then has a free float of zero.
That's what free float is.
It's how long an activity
can be delayed without
delaying the early start of the successor.
C is a successor of B.
Early start is this number here,
top left.
B finishes on day six, C will start on day
six.
So how long can B be delayed without
delaying the early start of C?
Zero.
So B has a total float of three,
but a free float of zero.
Right?
Now, again, let's think about this.
B and C are kind of like related.
Or rather, C is dependent on B.
So if you delay B, you will delay the
earliest start of C.
Naturally, right, since they share this
float, if B finishes on day seven,
C will start on day seven.
So that's what free float is.
How long an activity
can be delayed without
delaying the early
start of the next activity.
Now, the official formula is
early start of the successor
minus early finish of the
current, right, or the predecessor.
So early start of the successor between B
and C, C is a successor.
So the early start is C minus the early
finish of the current or the predecessor,
which is six.
Now, if that's easy to see when it's a
zero method, if it's a one method,
you have to remember to plus one.
So the other reason why one method is a
little bit more challenging.
Now, project float, let's talk about
project float.
Project float is how
long the entire project can
be delayed without impacting
some kind of deadline.
Now for this, they have to give you some
additional information.
Let's say the customer came to us and
said, we have to finish by day 21.
They've given us the date of day 21.
We have calculated our date of day 19.
our critical path is day 19.
So technically be delayed
by another two days and
that's not going to impact
the customer's deadline.
So we have a project float of two days.
So that is what project float refers to,
how long the entire
project can be delayed.
And like said, they have to give you this
additional piece of information.
They have to give you that deadline.
So technically then, if you wanted a
formula for that, is essentially,
project float is the deadline minus the
critical path.
So if our deadline is
day 21, critical path is 19,
so our project float then
is going to be two days.
Now, just as a little side note,
and again, a little exam tip, what
normally happens in reality, in reality
what normally happens, a lot of times
senior management will
give you a deadline and then
you will develop a schedule
based on that deadline.
And that is exactly what PMI standards
state that you should not be doing.
Senior management are not subject matter
experts.
So when it comes to any of the planning,
whether you're planning your budget,
whether you're planning your timeline,
your scope or whatever it is, you don't
just take senior management's word for it,
especially with the budget and the
timeline because they're not subject
matter experts.
right.
So senior management
might just give you some
unrealistic deadline,
some unrealistic budget.
And if you are basing your plan,
right, if you are planning your project
based on those unrealistic numbers,
then your project is already a failure.
So the correct approach is you utilize
subject matter experts to come up with
some kind of assessment, accurate
assessment or some kind of assessment,
you know, based on some
confidence level of when the project,
or rather of how long the
project will take or how much it will
cost if we're talking
about cost management.
And then you present that to your senior
management, to your customer, and that's
where the conversation should start,
not the other way around.
So always remember that.
You're a project manager.
So whether you are a command and control
project manager or whether you are a
servant leader in an agile project,
the key is collaboration.
You want to engage your stakeholders.
You want to collaborate with your
stakeholders, collaborate with team members.
So you don't just always blindly take
senior management's word for it.
So you utilize and
collaborate with subject matter
experts to come up with
an accurate assessment.
Okay, so these then were three types of
float, total float, free float,
project float.